Guide to the Vintage Equipment Collection RG.011
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Vintage Equipment Collection
Early-mid 20th century
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
RG.011
12 Cubic Feet 13 items
The items in this collection relate to the fields of electrical and civil engineering, as well as supplemental equipment, and were used by engineers in the early to mid 20th century.
Biographical / Historical
The items in this collection were transferred to the Poly Archives by various university departments. The most prominently represented departments include Civil Engineering and Electrical Engineering.
Scope and Contents
Equipment in this collection includes items civil and electrical engineers would have used in the early to mid 20th century. Surveying equipment, such as a theodolite and transit, as well as electrical engineering instruments, such as a decade capacitor, decade resistor, potentiometer, and volt meter are included. The equipment ranges in date from the early to mid 20th century.
Arrangement
Items in this collection are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is currently on display in the Bern Dibner Reading Room of the Bern Dibner Library of Science & Technology.
Please contact the archives to view items in this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; there is no documentation concerning the provenance of these materials.
Civil engineering; Surveying; Electrical engineering; Engineering; Kodak camera; Equipment and supplies; Radio -- Equipment and supplies; Brownie camera
- Series I: Vintage Equipment
  - Book Binding Stapler: Acme Stapling Co., Camden, NJ, undated (Object 1)
  - Current Transformer: Astra Corporation, Quincy, MA, undated (Object 2)
  - Decade Capacitor, Series 1575: Cornell-Dubilier Electronics Inc., Plainfield, NJ, circa 1940 (Object 3)
  - Decade Condenser Type 219-K: General Radio Co., Cambridge, MA, circa 1950 (Object 4)
  - Decade Resistor Type 1432-K: General Radio Co., Cambridge, MA, circa 1950 (Object 5)
  - Electrical Cables: Consolidated Edison Co., New York, NY, undated (Object 6)
  - Gauge: Airco, New York, NY, undated (Object 7)
  - Hawkeye Brownie Camera: Eastman Kodak, Rochester, NY, circa 1950 (Object 8)
  - Potentiometer: Leeds and Northrup Co., Philadelphia, PA, circa 1950 (Object 9)
  - Theodolite: Buff & Buff Mfg. Co., Boston, MA, undated (Object 10)
  - Transit: Buff & Buff Mfg. Co., Boston, MA, undated (Object 11)
    On Loan
    On loan to President Andrew Hamilton's Office, 4 February 2016
  - Volt Meter, Model 377: Simpson Electrical Co., Chicago, IL, circa 1950 (Object 12)
  - Wheatstone Bridge: Leeds and Northrup Co., Philadelphia, PA, undated (Object 13)
- Series II: 2021 Accretion, circa 1930-1965
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  These items were donated to the Poly Archives by Frank Baranowski's daughter, Susan Baranowski in February 2021. Accession 20-001.
  Arrangement
  This donation is housed in two boxes and arranged into two sub-series: Sub-series A: Engineering Equipment, circa 1930-1965 and Sub-series B: Academia, 1954. Items are listed alphabetically.
  Biographical / Historical
  Frank Baranowksi was born on November 1, 1921 in Bayonne, New Jersey and received a BS in Chemical Engineering from New York University Heights on June 5, 1943 and an MS from the University of Tennessee. Baranowski was a World War II vet and an engineer on the Manhattan Project. He passed away in Williamsburg, Virginia on August 30, 2017.
  Scope and Contents
  These items mainly include engineering equipment such as slide rules, drafting tools, and scales from the 1930s-1960s. They are located in bay 29 shelf 4C.
  - Sub-series A: Engineering Equipment, circa 1930-1965
    - Clay Adams Co. Scale with Weights in Wooden Box, circa 1940s (Box 1, Item 1)
    - Dietzgen Drafting Instruments (11 piece) in Black Case, circa 1930 (Box 1, Item 2)
    - Engineering Instruments Inc. 10-inch Slide Rule, undated (Box 1, Item 3)
    - Keuffel & Esser Beginner's Slide Rule, undated (Box 1, Item 4)
    - Keuffel & Esser Slide Rule and Leather Case with Instruction Booklet, circa 1940s (Box 1, Item 5)
    - Lutz Architect's Triangular Ruler, undated (Box 1, Item 6)
    - Sterling Slide Rule and Black Plastic Case, 1965 (Box 1, Item 7)
    - The Frederick Post Company Small Slide Rule and Leather Case, circa 1940s (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Sub-series B: Academia, 1954-06
    - Beginnings of Tau Beta Pi by Edwin S. Stackhouse, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - New York University Copy of June 5, 1943 Commencement, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Thesis Inserts and USB Drive Content Note, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Thesis: "Steady State Forced Heat Convection in Non-Compressible Fluids in Laminar Flow Through Circular Pipes," June 1954, 1954-06 (Box 2, Item 1)
    - USB Drive Containing Thesis Files, undated (Box 2, Item 2)